Guide to the Carlos Bulosan Papers
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
- Carlos Bulosan papers, 1936-1976, undated; 1948-1956; 0581-012; 4.65 cubic ft. 6 boxes; 9 negative microfilm reels,10 positive microfilm reels; 3 sound tape reels
  - Microfilm collection
    - Writings of Bulosan
      - Poems
        - "Into the world I walk free", undated (Reel 1)
        - "My Country", undated (Reel 1)
        - "My Street", undated (Reel 1)
        - "A Midnight Song", undated (Reel 1)
        - "All Summer", undated (Reel 1)
        - "A Hill. A House. and Love.", undated (Reel 1)
        - "Another April", undated (Reel 1)
        - "Discovery of a Minority", undated (Reel 1)
        - "Exits and Entrances for Our Time", undated (Reel 1)
        - ""I met her in the tall summertime"", undated (Reel 1)
        - "The Good Life: What Did I Know", undated (Reel 1)
      - Note, undated (Reel 1)
      - Poems
        - "Now That You are Still", undated (Reel 1)
        - "The Surrounded", undated (Reel 1)
        - "October 31, 1954", undated (Reel 1)
        - "Legend for Our Time", undated (Reel 1)
        - "Now that I lost you", undated (Reel 1)
        - "My New Room", undated (Reel 1)
        - "The time is too late", undated (Reel 1)
        - "The Song of Songs", undated (Reel 1)
        - "Peaceful You, Immortal You", undated (Reel 1)
        - "Our lives conflicted towards the end", undated (Reel 1)
        - "Lullabye and Goodnight", undated (Reel 1)
        - "Aha? on the Face of Love", undated (Reel 1)
        - "Song after Reading Harriet Tubman's Life", undated (Reel 1)
        - "A New Year Letter", undated (Reel 1)
        - "Poem for a Moment", undated (Reel 1)
        - "Desolation", undated (Reel 1)
        - "The Song of the Sun", undated (Reel 1)
        - "The Vaulted Wall", undated (Reel 1)
        - "A Nightfall Song", undated (Reel 1)
        - "Love Letter", undated (Reel 1)
        - "When Night Falls", undated (Reel 1)
        - "Song for Chris Mensalvas' Birthday - June 24, 1954", undated (Reel 1)
        - "The Masquerade Ball: A New Year's Eve Legend", undated (Reel 1)
        - "In Search of America", undated (Reel 1)
    - Outgoing Letters
      - Marjorie, undated; 1 item (Reel 1)
      - Chris, undated; 1 item (Reel 1)
      - Matt, undated; 1 item (Reel 1)
      - Mary Gibson, undated; 2 items (Reel 1)
        Includes poem for Maria.
      - Chris, undated; 1 item (Reel 1)
      - Mary Gibson, undated; (repeat copy) 2 items (Reel 1)
      - Florentino B. Valeros, 1953 February 8 (Reel 1)
        Partial bibliography attached.
    - Prose: "A Virgin for Cousin Pedro and Other Tales of Luzon", undated; 18 pages (Reel 1)
    - Poems "compiled for Chris and Irene", undated
      - "When I was a Little Boy: A Dream", undated (Reel 1)
      - "The Bee and the Rose", undated (Reel 1)
      - "When the Knife Cut You", undated (Reel 1)
      - "I Cannot Lose You", undated (Reel 1)
      - "White Rose, Wild Rose, Lost Rose", undated (Reel 1)
      - "When You Were a Little Girl", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Dark Moment", undated (Reel 1)
      - "The Blue Sky", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Testament", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Little Elegy", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Fear", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Desire", undated (Reel 1)
      - "My Country", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Growth", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Is It A Poem", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Silence", undated (Reel 1)
      - "My Mother", undated (Reel 1)
      - "But Eyes", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Cancione Maldeta", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Land of the Morning", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Can I Love You", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Of Love and Hate", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Unfinished Letter", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Will You be Men When You Grow Up", undated (Reel 1)
      - "There is only You in the Poem", undated (Reel 1)
      - "What Would You Do", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Adoration", undated (Reel 1)
      - "My People", undated (Reel 1)
      - "A Song of Freedom", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Gift", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Marching", undated (Reel 1)
      - "In the Moonlight", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Forever", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Little Song", undated (Reel 1)
      - "When I was a Little Boy: A Reality", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Praise and Warning", undated (Reel 1)
      - "A Little Poem", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Mother and Children", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Testament of Earth", undated (Reel 1)
      - "A Bright Star", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Miracle of Spring", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Passage from Life", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Land of Beauty", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Beautiful Boy", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Two Eternities", undated (Reel 1)
      - "How You are Still", undated (Reel 1)
      - "Only a Bird", undated (Reel 1)
    - Scrapbook, undated (Reel 2)
    - Textbook - Manila Bureau of Public Schools, Philippine Prose and Poetry(Volume 4, Manila. Bureau of Printing), 1951; 353 pages (Reel 3)
      Includes two of Carlos Bulosan's works: "My Father's Tragedy" and "If You Want to Know Who You Are." Microfilm includes 5 pages of notes from Bulosan to Josephine concerning authors and/or works found in the text
    - Manuscripts of Carlos Bulosan in the University of Chicago Library, undated (Reel 4)
    - Outgoing letters
      - Harriet Monroe (editor of Poetry Magazine), undated; 11 items (Reel 4)
        Includes brief biography, 1931-1936.
    - Poems
      - "Without Ceremony", undated (Reel 4)
      - "Letter from America", undated (Reel 4)
      - "In time of drought", undated (Reel 4)
      - "Secret", undated (Reel 4)
      - "No Story", undated (Reel 4)
      - "Monuments", undated (Reel 4)
    - General correspondence
      - Donald J. Paquette to Harriet, undated (Reel 4)
      - Monroe concerning Carlos Bulosan, 1936; 1 item (Reel 4)
    - Outgoing letters
      - Martin D. Zabell, 1937; 1 item (Reel 4)
      - Geraldine Volell, undated; 6 items (Reel 4)
      - George Dillon, undated; 5 items (Reel 4)
    - Poems
      - "The Young Man", undated (Reel 4)
      - "Night Piece", undated (Reel 4)
      - "Needing No Time", undated (Reel 4)
      - "The Phoenix", undated (Reel 4)
      - Three Poems:
        - "Letter in Exile", undated (Reel 4)
        - "American History", undated (Reel 4)
        - "Sunset and Evening Star", undated (Reel 4)
    - Play in verse - Jose Rizal (Reel 5)
    - Poems, undated
      - "All Summer", undated (Reel 5)
      - "A Hill. A House. And Love", undated (Reel 5)
      - "Always when I thought I found a sheltered sky", undated (Reel 5)
      - "Another April", undated (Reel 5)
      - "Another Letter to J.", undated (Reel 5)
      - "Discovery of a Memory", undated (Reel 5)
      - "Exits and Entrances for our Time", undated (Reel 5)
      - "In Remembrance", undated (Reel 5)
      - "My Country/My Street", undated (Reel 5)
      - "My New Room", undated (Reel 5)
      - "My Sister, My Bride", undated (Reel 5)
      - "The Oak Leaf", undated (Reel 5)
      - "Once Again I will Tell You", undated (Reel 5)
      - "Song for Chris Mensalvas' Birthday", undated (Reel 5)
      - "The Vaulted Wall", undated (Reel 5)
      - "A Walk through the Woods", undated (Reel 5)
      - "The Young Ones", undated (Reel 5)
    - Incoming letters
      - Valeros, Florentino E., 1955; 3 items (Reel 5)
      - Yabes, Leopoldo Y., 1948; 1 item (Reel 5)
      - Wally, undated; 1 item (Reel 5)
    - Outgoing Letters to Josephine Patrick, 1954, undated; 4 items (Reel 5)
      Originals in possession of Josephine Patrick.
    - Writings of Bulosan
      - Plays
        - The Big Silver Dollar, undated (Reel 6)
        - The Worldbeaters, undated (Reel 6)
      - Prose
        - "As Long as the Grass Shall Grow", undated (Reel 6)
      - Poetry
        - "Another Legend", undated (Reel 6)
        - "A Darkness. A Snowfall. A Rain", undated (Reel 6)
        - "Landscape With a Bottle", undated (Reel 6)
        - "Last Poem", undated (Reel 6)
        - "You will grow old together", undated (Reel 6)
    - Incoming letters
      - Bulosan, Aurelio, 1948; 4 items (Reel 6)
      - Bulosan, Marjorie Patton, 1953, undated; 6 items (Reel 6)
      - Committee to Sponsor (Luis) Taruc's Autobiography, 1953; 1 item (Reel 6)
      - Harcourt, Brace and Company, Publishers New York, 1955; 1 item (Reel 6)
      - Kunkel, Donald R., 1953; 1 item (Reel 6)
      - Lieber, Maxim, 1948; 1 item (Reel 6)
      - The Nation, 1958; 1 item (Reel 6)
      - Gaunders, Marion, 1949; 1 item (Reel 6)
      - Wilson (H. W.) Company, publishers, New York, 1953; 1 item (Reel 6)
      - Wolf, Harriet, 1948-1949; 5 items (Reel 6)
    - Outgoing letters, undated; 1 item (Reel 6)
    - General correspondence - Miscellaneous
      - Bulosan, Marjorie Patton, 1949, 1950, 1952; 4 items (Reel 6)
      - Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, International, Local 7-C, 1952; 2 items (Reel 6)
      - Josephine Patrick to Washington State Committee for the Protection of the Foreign Born, 1353 April 23; 1 item (Reel 6)
    - Financial records
      - Harcourt, Brace and Company, 1950; 1 item (Reel 6)
      - Lieber, Maxim, 1949; 1 item (Reel 6)
    - Lists
      - The Carlos Bulosan Fund, undated; 1 item (Reel 6)
    - Notes, undated; 1 item (Reel 6)
    - Ephemera, 1976; 3 items (Reel 6)
    - Publication: Saturday Evening Post special edition, 1943; 1 item (Reel 6)
      Including "Freedom from Want" by Bulosan.
    - Selections from prose writings, undated
      - "A rich man in the family", undated; 9 pages (Reel 7)
      - "The power of music", undated; 11 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Wisdom of Uncle Sator", undated; 19 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Betrayal of Uncle Soyoc", undated; 8 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Homecoming of Uncle Manuel", undated; 7 pages (Reel 7)
      - "A servant in the house", undated; 10 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Dinner with a king", undated; 9 pages, with two different copies of page 67 (Reel 7)
      - "The story of creation", undated; 100 pages (Reel 7)
      - "A trip to Baguio", undated; 16 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Marriage of Cousin Pedro", undated; 8 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Be American", undated; 9 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Bandit and the tax collector", undated; 8 pages (Reel 7)
      - "The betrayal of Uncle Roman", undated; 11 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Son of Uncle Sator", undated; 10 pages (Reel 7)
      - "I am not a laughing man", undated; 7 pages (Reel 7)
      - "My first day in America", undated; 3 pages (Reel 7)
      - "The summer of beautiful music", undated; 7 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Return of the amorous ghost", undated; 10 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Lonesome mermaid", undated; 8 pages (Reel 7)
      - "The great lover", undated; 10 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Springtime of my father", undated; 7 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Now long shadows were falling", undated; 61 pages (Reel 7)
      - "The big convention", undated; 26 pages (Reel 7)
      - "The amorous ghost came to town", undated; 9 pages (Reel 7)
      - "The beer drinkers", undated; 9 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Heart of darkness", undated; 4 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Tales from the old country", undated; 8 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Really, a ghost?", undated; 8 pages (Reel 7)
      - "The rooster's egg", undated; 14 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Unfinished portrait", undated; 9 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Cat in the rain", undated; 12 pages (Reel 7)
      - "The younger sister", undated; 18 pages (Reel 7)
      - "I don't know why", undated; 7 pages (Reel 7)
      - "My brother Joey", undated; 17 pages (Reel 7)
      - "The stolen violin", undated; 11 pages (Reel 7)
      - "The night reveals", undated; 12 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Death of an author", undated; 8 pages (Reel 7)
      - "I should have stood in bed", undated; 13 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Miracle by the sea", undated; 4 pages (Reel 7)
      - "The thief", undated; 12 pages (Reel 7)
      - "The glorious day", undated; 9 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Americano from Luzon", undated; 8 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Odyssey of Constantia Drake", undated; 10 pages (Reel 7)
      - "Romance of Magno Rubio", undated; 20 pages (Reel 7)
      - "We laugh a little", undated; 17 pages (Reel 7)
      - "The hairline of Pantaleon Cordalles Moradoro", undated; 20 pages (Reel 7)
      - "The worldbeaters", undated; 22 pages (Reel 7)
      - "The tall white horse", undated; 19 pages (Reel 7)
      - "The angel in Santo Domingo", undated; 22 pages (Reel 7)
      - "A city in the sky", undated; 26 pages (Reel 7)
    - Outgoing letters to Josephine Patrick, 1953-1955 (Reel 8)
    - "The Cry and the Dedication", undated (Reel 9)
- Sound recordings about Carlos Bulosan, 1959-1960; 0581-013; 2 sound cassettes (60 min. ea.); 2 CD-ROM discs
  Contains sound cassette and CD-ROM copies of recordings of individuals reminiscing about their friendship with Carlos Bulosan. The originals are reel-to-reel sound recordings (1959-1960) in Accession No. 0581-012.
  In the Chris Mensalvas interview conducted by Joseph Butterworth on September 19, 1959, Mensalvas stated his belief that Bulosan came to the United States in 1931 and landed in Seattle. He may have stayed in Seattle for a time but then went to Yakima to pick fruit. He wound up in Lompoc, California, where Mensalvas thinks they first met. When Carlos was unemployed, he lived with Mensalvas, as did Aurelio, Carlos's brother. This housing consisted of a two bedroom apartment with a kitchen, shared by four men.
  Jo Patrick, Barry Hatten and Red Gibb recall Carlos Bulosan's later years in an interview recorded at Mary Gibson's apartment on June 19, 1960.
  Listening equipment necessary for cassette audio tapes or CD-ROM. Contact Special Collections for details.
  Copied July 31, 1997, July 2007
- Carlos Bulosan papers, 1953; 0581-014; 0.03 cubic feet 1 vertical file
  Autographed manuscript poem "The language of flowers" (for Victor Cabebe), with letter to Josephine Patrick on verso (Seattle, 1953 April 14).
  Donor: Mary Gibson Hatten, April 27, 2007
- Ralph Franklin postcard, 1963; 0581-015; 0.03 cubic feet 1 vertical file
  Postcard from Ralph Franklin to Mary Gibson regarding his abandoning of Carlos Bulosan dissertation.
  Open to all users
  Donor: Mary Hatten, October 11, 2011